<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Papers on Øystein Sørensen</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Papers on Øystein Sørensen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/papers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Cycles, Trends and Time-Varying Effects in Dynamic Structural Equation Models with Regression Splines</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper12/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper12/</guid>
      <description>This paper considers rank and preference modeling for the case in which data arrive sequentially, rather than in a batch. The goal is to compute the posterior distribution incrementally in time, so that it can be quickly updated when new data arrives. To this end, we develop a sequential Monte Carlo algorithm for the Bayesian Mallows model. arXiv preprint currently under revision.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sequential Rank and Preference Learning with the Bayesian Mallows Model</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper11/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper11/</guid>
      <description>This paper considers rank and preference modeling for the case in which data arrive sequentially, rather than in a batch. The goal is to compute the posterior distribution incrementally in time, so that it can be quickly updated when new data arrives. To this end, we develop a sequential Monte Carlo algorithm for the Bayesian Mallows model. arXiv preprint currently under revision.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multilevel Semiparametric Latent Variable Modeling in R with &#34;galamm&#34;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper10/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper10/</guid>
      <description>This paper presents the R package &amp;#34;galamm&amp;#34;, which contains open-source implementations for generalized additive latent and mixed models (GALAMMs). Published in Multivariate Behavioral Research.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Longitudinal Modeling of Age-Dependent Latent Traits with Generalized Additive Latent and Mixed Models</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper9/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper9/</guid>
      <description>This paper was motivated by the need to use flexible spline models to model how cognitive abilities change with age, and investigating how changes in abilities in certain cognitive domains can be explained by changes in the brain. To this end we developed a framework called Generalized Additive Latent and Mixed Models (GALAMM), combining generalized additive mixed models, structural equation modeling, and mxied effect modeling. We also propose algorithms for estimating the models, using sparse matrix methods and automatic differentation. Published in Psychometrika.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A recipe for accurate estimation of lifespan brain trajectories, distinguishing longitudinal and cohort effects</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper8/</guid>
      <description>This paper considers estimation of lifespan brain trajectories from longitudinal data, using generalized additive mixed models. It studies how to distinguish longitudinal effects from cohort effects, and shows example code in R which practitioners can use for their own data. Published in NeuroImage.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meta-analysis of generalized additive models in neuroimaging studies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper7/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper7/</guid>
      <description>This paper considers meta analysis of nonlinear functions estimated by generalized additive (mixed) models.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BayesMallows: An R Package for the Bayesian Mallows Model</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper5/</guid>
      <description>This paper presents the BayesMallows R package, for analysis of rank and preference data. Published in the R Journal.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From observed laterality to latent hemispheric differences: Revisiting the inference problem</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper6/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper6/</guid>
      <description>This paper considers predicting whether people are right or left brain dominant for language processing, based on their result in dichotic listening experiments as well as their handedness.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>hdme: High-Dimensional Regression with Measurement Error</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper4/</guid>
      <description>This paper presents the hdme package, implementing variable selection methods for regression with covariate measurement error.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Covariate Selection in High-Dimensional Generalized Linear Models With Measurement Error</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper2/</guid>
      <description>This paper proposes an extension of the generalized Dantzig selector for cases with measurement error in the predictor variables.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probabilistic preference learning with the Mallows rank model</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper3/</guid>
      <description>This paper consider probabilistic preference learning with Mallows&amp;#39; rank model.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement Error in Lasso: Impact and Likelihood Bias Correction</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/paper1/</guid>
      <description>This paper analyzes the impact of covariate measurement error in the lasso method for penalized regression, and then proposes correction methods both for linear models and generalized linear models.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
